

Yarik Menchaca Resendiz

Stuttgart, Germany

Website

LinkedIn:

https://www.linkedin.com/in/yarik-menchaca-resendiz-ba2466115/

GitHub: https://github.com/ YarikMR

Cellphone: +49 (0) 151 47565395

E-mail:

Yarik.MenchacaR@gmail.com Yarik.Menchaca-Resendiz@ims.uni-stuttgart.de

PROFILE

I'm a Ph.D. candidate in Computational Linguistics with a focus on NLP, LLMs, and AI. I have experience in both academic and industry research, specializing in AI/ML development, prompt optimization, and NLP application deployment. I enjoy applying my skills to solve practical problems through research and AI-driven solutions.

EDUCATION

University of Stuttgart

Ph.D. in Computational Linguistics.

Jul 2021 - Dec 2024

Instituto Politecnico Nacional Master's degree in Computer Science. Graduate in December 2017

GPA 9.8/10

Instituto Politecnico Nacional

Bachelors in computer engineering.

Graduate in December 2015 GPA 8.3/10

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant | Otto-Friedrich-Universität Bamberg, Germany

Apr 2024 - Present

Conducted research on prompt optimization methods for language models and managed cloud GPU server environments for large-scale language model deployment.

Graduate Teaching Assistant | University of Stuttgart, Germany

Apr 2022 - Mar 2024

Taught, evaluated, and supervised bachelor's and master's students in Natural Language Processing courses, including Information Retrieval and Teamlab, focusing on practical applications and research mentorship.

Data Scientist | Kantar, Mexico

Jun 2018 - Oct 2021

Researched and developed AI/ML methodologies for large language models, chatbots, text mining, basket analysis, and prediction.

- Created a natural language processing application for 10 languages.
- Implemented machine learning techniques such as deep neural networks, regression, and decision trees.

Research Intern | University of Wolverhampton, UK

Feb 2017 - Aug 2017

Developed a sentiment analysis application for Spanish texts.

PUBLICATIONS

- IMS medicALY at #SMM4H 2024: Detecting impacts of outdoor spaces on social anxiety with data augmented ensembling. In Dongfang Xu and Graciela Gonzalez-Hernandez, editors, Proceedings of The 9th Social Media Mining for Health Research and Applications (SMM4H 2024) Workshop and Shared Tasks, pages 83--87, Bangkok, Thailand, August 2024. Association for Computational Linguistics.
- What makes medical claims (un)verifiable? analyzing entity and relation properties for fact verification. In Yvette Graham and Matthew Purver, editors, Proceedings of the 18th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers), pages 2046--2058, St. Julian's, Malta, March 2024. Association for Computational Linguistics.
- Affective natural language generation of event descriptions through fine-grained appraisal conditions. In Proceedings of the 16th International Conference on Natural Language Generation, Prague, Czech Republic, September 2023. Association for Computational Linguistics.
- Emotion-conditioned text generation through automatic prompt optimization. In Proceedings of the 1st Workshop on Taming Large Language Models: Controllability in the era of Interactive Assistants!, Prague, Czech Republic, September 2023. Association for Computational Linguistics.

LANGUAGES

French: Advanced Spanish: Native language English: Advanced Italian: Basic

German: Basic

SKILLS

Programming languages

8 years: Python 5 years: Git

1 year: C++, C#, Java, MYSQL, R, .Net 3 years: Docker, Microsoft Azure

COURSES & CERTIFICATIONS

Python programmer Jr. Artificial Intelligence Foundations: Thinking Machines

Deep Learning in Python Custom Model, Layers, and Loss Functions with TensorFlow

Advance Deep Learning with Keras Introduction to Recommender Systems

Learning TensorFlow with JavaScript

Building Deep Learning Applications with Keras 2.0

Introduction to Deep Learning with OpenCV

Natural LanguageProcessing

Design database MYSQL

R Statistics Essential Training

TensorFlow Developer Linux administrator Introduction to TensorFlow for Artificial Intelligence. Introduction to R

Sequences, Time Series and Prediction Data Analysis in R, the data table Way

Natural Language Processing in TensorFlow Big Data Processing, Data exploration with Scala and Apache Spark

Convolutional Neural Networks in TensorFlow Financial Markets
Machine Learning for Marketing: Essential Training

THESIS SUPERVISION

Master Thesis - Plug and Play Domain Adaptation for Neural Machine Translation

Jan 2023 - Dec 2023

Emīls Kadiķis